<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-07-03T00:12:52+0000</published>

	<id>f6785e5e-bfa5-43e0-8dbd-d6604bda0bad</id>

	<category term="Genetics" />

	<title>2nd Cousin (or 1st Cousin Once Removed) on 23andMe</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			<a rel="nofollow" href="http://23andme.com/">23andMe</a> has various tools for genealogy.
			Among them is their <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.23andme.com/you/relfinder/">relative finder</a> tool.
		</p>
		<p>
			23andMe's <em>relative finder</em> tool uses DNA to figure out who could (potentially) be a relative of yours.
			As I write this, 985 people show up there for me.
			(For those interested in the technical details, you can read about how it's done <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0034267">here</a>.)
		</p>
		<p>
			The tool (by default) orders your matches by closeness of relation.
			My mother and brother (who also have their DNA scanned on 23anMe) are (not surprisingly) at the top of this list.
			Ignoring them though, here is the person at the top of the list:
		</p>
		<p style="text-align:ceter;">
			<img src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/07/03/2nd_cousin_on_23andme/23andme-2nd-cousin.png" />
		</p>
		<p>
			(The name isn't given, because, by default, 23andMe does not show people's name in <em>relative finder</em> without their permission.)
		</p>
		<p>
			The DNA percentage match I have with this person -- 5.81% -- puts the person in the <em>2nd cousin</em> and even the <em>1st cousin once removed range</em>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Now, I should say that I have tried contacting this person (on 23andMe), but the person has not responed back.
			(I find this very unfortunate, from a personal point-of-view, as I would very much like to know who this relative is, and, how we are related.)
		</p>

		<h2>The DNA Evidence</h2>
		<p>
			So, what do I know about this person, based on the very limited information I have....
		</p>
		<p>
			Just from that 23andMe record, I know that:
		</p>
		<p>
			#1: The person is a male.
		</p>
		<p>
			#2: The percentage of DNA we share: <em>5.81%</em>.
		</p>
		<p>
			#3: The Y-DNA haplogroup of the person: <em>J1</em>.
		</p>
		<p>
			#4: The mtDNA halogroup of the person: <em>HV</em>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Using information beyond that 23andMe record, I know that....
		</p>
		<p>
			My mother has her DNA scanned on 23andMe, and this person does <b>not</b> show up for her (on 23andMe's <em>relative finder</em> tool), therefore this person would have to be from my father's side of the family.
			(My father past away, so I can't get his DNA scanned.)
		</p>
		<p>
			mtDNA is passed down from mothers to their children.
			We happen to share the same mtDNA haplogroup -- mtDNA haplogroup HV -- but that is just a coincidence, since we already know that this person is not related to my mother.
		</p>
		<p>
			Only males have Y-DNA.
			(Females do not.)
			Y-DNA is passed down from father to son.
			23andMe has indicated <a href="http://changelog.ca/offhand/2011/04/28/23andme">my Y-DNA haplogroup is R1b1b2a1a1d1*</a>.
			This (potential) relative has a Y-DNA haplogroup of J1; which is very different than my Y-DNA haplogroup.
			Therefore, this puts limits on the ways we could be related.
		</p>
		<p>
			(For example, because we have different Y-DNAs, this could <b>not</b> be my father's brother's (hypothetical) son's son.
			Just to say it explicitly and avoid any confusion for any relatives that may read this, as far as I know, my father's brother did not have any children; thus why I'm calling it "hypothetical".)
		</p>
		<p>
			I'd very much like to know who this is.
		</p>


		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
