<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2013-03-27T01:16:27-07:00</published>

	<id>bb1bb18d-2989-40a3-b38b-5b09eb44548c</id>

	<category term="Computer Science" />
	<category term="Software Engineering" />

	<title>Am I A Software Engineer Or Computer Scientist?</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			Should I call myself a <em>Software Engineer</em> or a <em>Computer Scientist</em>?
		</p>
		<p>
			Something I found out recently is that some universities have an actual Software Engineering program that is separate from their Computer Science program.
		</p>
		<p>
			When I was in university, you took Computer Science and became a Software Engineer.
			There was no Software Engineering program (separate from Computer Science), <abbr title="Simon Fraser University">at least at the University I went to</abbr>.
			Back then (<abbr title="Simon Fraser University">at the University I went to</abbr>) studying Computer Science required you to also take (and pass) some courses on formal Engineering practice.
		</p>
		<p>
			Back then, Computer Science was (also) in the middle of transitioning from being dominated by Mathematicians.
			(I was on that Math side of it.)
			And way very Math heavy.
			Which was OK with me, as I also had a formal Math background :-)
		</p>
		<p>
			This goes into a topic I was discussing with someone a few weeks ago:
			<strong>should someone with a Computer Science background call themselves a <em>Software Engineer</em> or <em>Computer Scientist</em></strong>?
		</p>
		<p>
			Although my experience may not be representative, I have never heard anyone with a Computer Science degree working in industry call themselves a Computer Scientist.
			In my experience, the norm for someone with a Computer Science degree working in industry is to call themselves a Software Engineer (and sometimes, a label which I really dislike because it is so vague to the point that it is almost meaningless, a Software Developer).
		</p>
		<p>
			Perhaps this is a generational thing.
			Software Engineering was part of Computer Science when I was in school still. 
			And Computer Science was still Math-heavy.
			Maybe it is not like that anymore.
		</p>
		<p>
			I guess I should say that conceptually, <em>Computer Scientist</em> and <em>Software Engineer</em> are not mutually exclusive labels.
			Conceptually, you could be both.
		</p>
		<p>
			(I have also seen a new term being thrown around: "<em>Data Scientist</em>".
			From the definitions I have seen for this, many Software Engineers qualify for this too, including myself.
			Although there does seem to be <strong>a lot</strong> of hype built up around <em>Data Science</em>.)
		</p>


		<address class="vcard" itemscope="1" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" itemprop="name url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name" itemprop="givenName">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name" itemprop="additionalName">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name" itemprop="familyName">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
