<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2013-01-24T08:39:01-0800</published>

	<id>3b3486d6-d15d-445b-bac8-a3a83426dc80</id>

	<category term="Artificial Intelligence" />
	<category term="Computer Science" />
	<category term="Machine Learning" />
	<category term="Morality" />
	<category term="Politics" />
	<category term="Psychology" />

	<title>Moral-Laden Algorithmic Writing</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			For the last while I have seen a hand full of stories talking about <em>algorithmic writing</em>, for journalism, for books, etc.
			Basically software that'll create a magazine article or a book all by itself without a human's help.
			And the quality seems pretty good.
		</p>
		<p>
			Reading some of the press surrounding this <em>algorithmic writing</em>, it makes it sound like it is something new,
			<strong>but</strong> it really isn't.
			<em>Algorithmic writing</em> has been used for quite a while in "gaming" search engines.
		</p>

		<h2>Algorithmic Writing and Morality</h2>
		<p>
			But on the topic of <em>algorithmic writing</em>, I think it would be interesting and even useful to create an <em>algorithmic writing</em> system that can create <em>moral-laden</em> writing for different moral frameworks.
		</p>
		<p>
			It would be even more useful if combined with technology that can detect a person's moral framework.
		</p>

		<h2>Online Social Networks</h2>
		<p>
			With respect to creating such a system, if people have a presence on (online) social networks, there's a lot of analysis you could do.
		</p>
		<p>
			For a simple example, look for communities (in the graph theory sense of the word).
			Although most community detection algorithms are non-convergent, so look for 'community cores' instead.
		</p>
		<p>
			One could even use the text (or video or audio, etc) associated with the 'community core' to feed into the <em>algorithmic writing</em> system.
		</p>

		<h2>Other Strategies</h2>
		<p>
			Although that is something I consider "low hanging fruit" from an algorithmic point of view.
		</p>
		<p>
			There's other "low hanging fruit", from an algorithmic point of view, too.
			And with some offline and online analysis work, via a machine learning system and help of humans, one could improve said algorithmic writing system <em>a lot</em>.
			(At least in part, taking an interative, trial-and-error approach to developing the system could be useful.)
		</p>
		<p>
			And just to say it explicitly, there's different sources of data that could be used.
			(Online) social networks is just one example.
			I'm not trying to be exhaustive.
		</p>


		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
