<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2011-09-11T08:39:26+0000</published>

	<id>339b6bc7-d2f1-4a65-9955-0359f5edf963</id>

	<category term="Morality" />
	<category term="Politics" />
	<category term="Psychology" />

	<title>Jealousy And "Spreading The Wealth"? N=1</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			I've been interested in Moral Psychology for a while now.
			In particular the work of those developing <a rel="nofollow" href="http://moralfoundations.org/">Moral Foundation theory</a>.
			(But also others working in the field.)
		</p>
		<p>
			With respect to left-liberals / progressives politics and morality, I have sometimes read people claiming that their egalitarianism is driven by jealousy.
			I've been inclined to dismiss these jealousy claims as probably being Ad Hominem.
			(Or at best, other simply not understanding left-liberals / progressives moral cognitions.)
		</p>
		<p>
			A conversation with a close friend about <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/story/2011/09/01/bc-cars-impounded.html">something that was being talking about in the news</a> has prompted me to be open to the '<em>driven by jealousy</em>' claim.
			Basically a bunch of young adults were racing very very expensive cars, and the impression is that money isn't an issue for any of them.
		</p>
		<p>
			The relevance of this is in regards to a conversation I had with a long time friend of mine about those young adults with expensive cars.
			(I "wrote" down the conversation on my phone right after it because although it's N=1 it made me more open to the '<em>driven by jealousy</em>' claim.)
		</p>
		<p>
			<strong>Friend</strong>: "<i>they don't deserve it [the expensive cars], they should spread the wealth.</i>"
		</p>
		<p>
			<strong>Me</strong>: "<i>there are a lot of crackies who you have more wealth than. should you be made to spread your wealth to them?</i>"
		</p>
		<p>
			<strong>Friend</strong>: "<i>no</i>"
		</p>
		<p>
			<strong>Me</strong>: "<i>then why should they [those people with the expensive cars] be made to spread their wealth?</i>"
		</p>
		<p>
			(And before I post his response to this question let me say I've known him for a LONG time.
			About a decade at the time of writing this.
			And he tends to be very straight forward with me;
			sometimes to the point of way way <abbr title="too much information">TMI</abbr>.
			)
		</p>
		<p>
			<strong>Friend</strong>:
			"<i>because I'm jealous. they have something I want.</i>"
		</p>
		<p>
			Now obviously, this proves nothing!
			This is N=1 and could be unrepresentative.
			Etc.
			(And, as far as I know, he doesn't self-identify as a left-lberal or progressive.
			It's even possible that this could "say" more about those who "support" left-liberals / progressives policies rather than those that self-identify as left-liberals / progressives.)
			<em>But</em>, I previously dismissed the jealousy claim as Ad Hominem before;
			I am now open to it.
		</p>

		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
