<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2011-10-23T19:15:55-0700</published>

	<id>22ba5ca8-0b71-418a-8ea6-39ced6b61583</id>

	<category term="Mathematics" />
	<category term="MathML" />
	<category term="Web Development" />

	<title>MathML Invisible Times</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			In mathematics we often don't bother writing the multiplication operator. For example, we tend not to write:
		</p>
		<figure>
			<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
				<mrow>
					<mn>
						2
					</mn>
					<mo>
						&#215;
					</mo>
					<mi>
						n
					</mi>
				</mrow>
			</math>
		</figure>
		<p>
			But instead often simply write:
		</p>
		<figure>
			<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
				<mrow>
					<mn>
						2
					</mn>
					<mo>
						&#8290;
					</mo>
					<mi>
						n
					</mi>
				</mrow>
			</math>
		</figure>
		<p>
			When writing MathML markup, you could put the "2" and the "n" next to each other, and make it look the way you want, <strong>but that would not be semantically correct</strong>.
			And if you are bothering with MathML then you probably want some level of semantic correctness.
		</p>

		<p>
			(Note, at the time of writing, not all web browsers support MathML. If you create MathML you are probably aware of this. However, I am noting this because there is MathML code in this article that will only look "good" if your browser supports MathML.)
		</p>

		<h2>Invisible Times</h2>
		<p>
			In MathML we can use the <em>invisible times</em> character to get the look we want, while being semantically correct.
		</p>
		<p>
			The <em>MathML invisible times</em> can be created with the following XML entity:
		</p>
		<figure>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr>
						<th style="border:1px solid;padding:0.5em;font-weight:bold;">
							Name
						</th>
						<th style="border:1px solid;padding:0.5em;font-weight:bold;">
							Decimal Entity
						</th>
						<th style="border:1px solid;padding:0.5em;font-weight:bold;">
							Hexidecimal Entity
						</th>
					</tr>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<tr>
						<td style="border:1px solid;padding:0.5em;">
							Invisible Times
						</td>
						<td style="border:1px solid;padding:0.5em;">
							&amp;#8290;
						</td>
						<td style="border:1px solid;padding:0.5em;">
							&amp;#x2062;
						</td>
					</tr>
				</tbody>
			</table>
		</figure>
		<p>
			The <em>MathML invisible times</em> character (theoretically) actually works in all XML languages (such as RSS, Atom, OPML, etc), since it comes from UNICODE.
			(I.e., the <em>invisible times</em> character is actually the UNICODE <em>invisible times</em> character that, like all XML-based languages, MathML supports.)
		</p>
		<p>
			(In addition to working in MathML and other XML-based markups, this entity will also work in HTML.)
		</p>

		<h2>Warning</h2>
		<p>
			There is also a MathML entity name for the <em>invisible times</em> character: <code class="mathml">&amp;InvisibleTimes;</code>.
			<strong>I recommend AGAINST using this named version of the entity.</strong>
			The reason is that if your MathML code gets embedded into other kinds of markup (like HTML, Atom, RSS, other XML, etc)
			using the <code class="mathml">&amp;InvisibleTimes;</code> version of the entity may actually break things (due to invalid XML).
			(I'll skip the technical details, but if you're interested it relates to <abbr title="Document Type Definition">DTD</abbr>s.)
			For this reason <strong>I strongly recommend FOR using the <code class="mathml">&amp;#8290;</code></strong> entity whenver you want to create an <em>invisible times</em>.
		</p>
		<p>
			If that last paragraph didn't make sense, just ignore it.
			The take-away-message is simply to use the <code class="mathml">&amp;#8290;</code> entity to create an <em>invisible times</em>.
		</p>

		<h2>Example</h2>
		<p>
			Here's sample MathML markup using the <em>invisible times</em> character:
		</p>
		<pre><code>
&lt;mrow&gt;
    &lt;mn&gt;
        5
    &lt;/mn&gt;
    &lt;mo&gt;
        <em>&amp;#8290;</em>
    &lt;/mo&gt;
    &lt;mi&gt;
        n
    &lt;/mi&gt;
&lt;/mrow&gt;
		</code></pre>
		<p>
			Which gives you:
		</p>
		<figure>
			<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
				<mrow>
					<mn>
						5
					</mn>
					<mo>
						&#8290;
					</mo>
					<mi>
						n
					</mi>
				</mrow>
			</math>
		</figure>

		<h2>The Pith</h2>
		<p>
			So, the <em>MathML invisible times</em> is created by using the <code>&amp;#8290;</code> entity.
		</p>

		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
