<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-09-10T12:00:00-0700</published>

	<id>6966d43c-5c67-427a-9aba-931d42276b89</id>

	<category term="HootSuite" />
	<category term="Owly" />

	<title>HootSuite</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			For a while now I've been involved with what became the successful startup known as <a rel="nofollow" href="http://hootsuite.com/">HootSuite</a>.
			Today, officially, I no longer <em>work at</em> HootSuite.
		</p>


		<h2>Change</h2>
		<p>
			Job changes can be seen as milestones in people's lives.
			But, for HootSuite too, as far as anyone seems to know, although I am not the first person to leave HootSuite, I am the first <em>senior</em> person to leave the company.
		</p>
		<p>
			Stuff like this happens as companies get big(ger).
			And HootSuite has gotten a lot bigger!
			No longer is everyone sitting in the same room, with plenty of extra space.
			It's office<strong>s</strong> span either side of a street.
			And there's even an office in England now.
		</p>

		<h2>History</h2>
		<p>
			(My history with HootSuite is really through <a href="http://beiercai.com/">Beier Cai</a>, so he's going to come up quite a bit.)
		</p>
		<p>
			What most people might not know is that my history with what became HootSuite started <em>before</em> HootSuite was actually created.
		</p>
		<p>
			Back in 2007/2008 a handful of us, who are at HootSuite now, worked together at a company called <a rel="nofollow" href="http://navarik.com/">Navarik</a>.
			(<a href="http://changelog.ca/" title="Charles Iliya Krempeaux">Myself</a>,
			<a href="http://beiercai.com/" title="Beier Cai">Beier</a>,
			<a href="http://flickr.com/gwilli/" title="Greg Williams">Greg</a>,
			<a href="http://twitter.com/bmonkman" title="Bill Monkman">Bill</a>,
			<a href="http://twitter.com/noelpullen" title="Noel Pullen">Noel</a>,
			<a href="http://twitter.com/elthue" title="Louisa Thue">Louisa</a>,
			and <a href="http://radogazo.com/">Rado</a>.)
		</p>
		<p>
			The person who is HootSuite's original &amp; principal software engineer (and now Chief Architect) -- Beier Cai -- and I sat next to each other, over at Navarik.
			(Back then Beier was a junior software engineer.)
		</p>
		<p>
			Back then, I had come to Navarik during a phase when I was freelancing.
			In a nutshell, it was after I closed down my 3rd company, and before I started my 4th company.
			It was also a time after I had already gone through another startup (which I didn't start but was the lead &amp; principal software engineer at), which eventually ended up in the hands of Microsoft, after Microsoft bought aQuantive.
		</p>
		<p>
			When I left Navarik, I wanted to keep in touch with a number of the people I had become friends with, which included Beier.
			I got a number of them to join what was then (outside of tech circles) an obscure social network called <a rel="nofollow" href="http://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Fast forward a bit, I was just starting to transition away from freelancing and starting my 4th company (with Rado) and Beier ended up at a company called <a rel="nofollow" href="http://invokemedia.com/">Invoke</a>.
			(It was under the company Invoke, that HootSuite was created.)
		</p>
		<p>
			Here's an e-mail Beier sent Rado and I back in July 7th, 2008:
		</p>
		<blockquote>
			<p>
				Hello guys,
			</p>
			<p>
				I started working with a company called InvokeMedia last week, it was the one Noel introduced me, so far is has been good.
				How are you guying doing?
				Charles are you looking for a new contracting job or working with Rado on starting your own company?
			</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			Time passed, <a href="http://twitter.com/invoker" title="Ryan Holmes">Ryan</a> eventually asks Beier if he could build what is now called HootSuite, but then called BrightKit.
		</p>
		<p>
			My <strong><u>extremely</u></strong> minor role in that event is that I happened to introduce Beier to Twitter earlier that year.
		</p>
		<p>
			But having been the one to introduce Beier to Twitter meant I was his "go to guy" for Twitter advice and helping him test the system.
			(I was also a very heavy Twitter user back then.)
		</p>
		<p>
			In addition to that, with the previous startup I mentioned, I had created a system that was somewhat comparable to HootSuite's architecture.
			So I was also someone with whom Beier could talk to about system architecture (since I'd already dealt with and solved many of these problems before).
		</p>
		<p>
			Here's an excerpt from another e-mail from Beier to me in November 28th, 2008, after I first noticed the <a href="http://ow.ly/">ow.ly</a> URL shortener being used in <a href="http://twitter.com/beiercai">his twitter feed</a>:
		</p>
		<blockquote>
			<p>
				Yes, that's something from my work.
				I'm currently lead the development of two projects, ow.ly and brightkit.com (the logo for brightkit.com is an owl, that's how we came up with ow.ly).
				both will go public soon.
				ow.ly is for url shortening and stats collection.
				[...]
				Brightkit.com is for twitter advertising [...]
				Actually I'm planning to send you guys emails helping me promote these two websites, stay tuned! (o;
			</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			On December 1st, 2008 I received an invite for HootSuite (which was called BrightKit back then).
			And my involvement with HootSuite, beyond the level of a muse, began.
			I was a user and beta (or perhaps alpha) tester.
		</p>
		<p>
			In February 27th, 2009, (while I was on vacation in <a href="http://changelog.ca/album/2009/02/11/vacation_in_buenos_aires_argentina_2009">Argentina</a>) Beier sent me an e-mail.
			Here's an excerpt from that e-mail:
		</p>
		<blockquote>
			<p>
				[..]
			</p>
			<p>
				A new plan for Hootsuite [...]
				What we are planning to do is to have a customizable multi-column interface.
				By customizable multi-column, I mean users can group multiple columns under a single group name, for example, you can group Home|Reply|DM under the group name 'reiver'.
				But let say you have two Twitter profiles for work, profileA and profileB, then you can group profileA's Home|Reply and profileB's Home|Reply together and give it a group name called 'My Work', which is now a 4 column view.
				This will add lots of values for users with multiple Twitter profiles.
				You can switch from one group to another at any time.
				And you can choose to view a subset of a group's columns.
				For example if you have a group with 8 columns, 3 can be visible at the same time, the other 5 will be hidden.
				Another thing we'll do is, for each active/visible column, we'll auto refresh the Twitter feed every 5 minutes.
			</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			(The <a href="http://twitter.com/reiver">reiver</a> Beier was talking about is <a href="http://twitter.com/reiver">my twitter feed</a>, BTW.)
		</p>
		<p>
			Meanwhile, while all this HootSuite/BrightKit stuff was going on, Rado and I created what was my 4th company.
			(Although, really there were a couple other side businesses I don't really count. But if you count those I suppose it was my 6th.)
			We worked hard, the company grew to 13 people.
			I operated as the company's <em>Director of Engineering</em>.
			(The company was pretty much <em>all</em> a development team.)
		</p>
		<p>
			After 3 years, Rado and I shut down that company,
			I left there, and after talking to Beier a bit, I came to HootSuite.
			(Beier had actually tried to get me to join HootSuite before that.
			But this time certain things made it a good choice for me.)
		</p>
		<p>
			HootSuite was small back then.
			This was pre- the funding that lead to the mass hiring spree!
		</p>
		<p>
			The company still really hadn't compartmentalized yet.
			<a href="http://twitter.com/jorobot" title="Joanna Ambrosio">Joa</a><a href="http://www.matikarevista.com/" title="Joanna Ambrosio">nna</a> (in Community/Marketing) and I (in Engineering) used to sit next to each other.
			This was before she moved over to sit next to <a href="http://uncleweed.net/" title="Dave Olson">Dave</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/Jesswakeman" title="Jessica Wakeman">Jess</a> (in the community/marketing area of the room).
		</p>

		<h2>HootSuite Trivia</h2>
		<p>
			BTW, for yet more HootSuite trivia, Jess was the first girl at HootSuite.
			Beier is (currently) the only person for whom there exist an Owly made in his image;
			although, it is not his "normal" image, but something that happened at <a href="http://changelog.ca/album/2011/07/01/galiano_island_retreat">the first HootSuite retreat</a>.
			I suppose I can also mention that <a href="http://twitter.com/pdon" title="Paul Donnell">Paul</a> is the one who originally Owly; although Joanna and even <a href="http://twitter.com/stephawie">Steph</a><a href="http://www.thedandeliontheory.com/">anie</a> have took over the task of created newer ones.
			There is an "<em>easter egg</em>" in the HootSuite web app; if you search <a href="http://changelog.ca/log">my blog</a> you can find a pretty good hint about it.
			There are usually a number of dogs in the office, and many of them have twitter accounts; for example:
			<a href="http://twitter.com/MikaHoots">Mika</a>,
			<a href="http://twitter.com/tulliveranne">Tully</a>,
			and
			<a href="http://twitter.com/MontyPug">Monty</a>.
			From time to time the office erupts into <em>spontaneous clapping</em>; eventually a twitter account was created so people could figure out why they were clapping.
		</p>

		<h2>Bye HootSuite</h2>
		<p>
			Although certain people knew about it at the beginning of August, it was on August 21st, 2012 that it was announced to the company.
			In front of the entire engineering and development team it was announced that I'd be leaving.
		</p>
		<p style="text-align:center;">
			<a href="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/09/10/hootsuite/clappingowls.png"><img
				src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/09/10/hootsuite/clappingowls.png"
				alt="Clapping yesterday in Dev room around 2:45pm: It was announced that Charles is leaving HS, to head Engineering dept at another local startup"
				style="width:70%;"
			/></a>
			<br />
			<a
				href="http://twitter.com/ClappingOwls/status/238306666125352960"
				title="Clapping yesterday in Dev room around 2:45pm: It was announced that Charles is leaving HS, to head Engineering dept at another local startup"
			>tweet</a>
		</p>
		<p>
			I find it a bit strange that I'm considered one of the original people in HootSuite.
			To me, Beier Cai and Paul Donnelly (along with the founders) are the originals.
			But I suppose if you were pre- the funding that led to the <em>hiring spree</em>, you're an <em>original</em>.
		</p>
		<p>
			So I say <em>good bye</em> to HootSuite.
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, "<em>good bye</em> to HootSuite" in a professional capacity at least.
			I have a lot of friends that still work at HootSuite.
			And I'm sure I'll be at the office from time to time.
		</p>
		<p style="text-align:center;">
			<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/gwilli/6894949286/sizes/o/in/photostream/"><img
				src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/09/10/hootsuite/hootsuite_foosball.jpg"
				style="width:70%;"
			/></a>
			<br />
			(In the photo, me in the top-right in the striped shirt, where you can't see my face.)
		</p>
		<!--
		<p>
			So I say <em>see you around</em> and <em>see you later</em> to
			(in alphabetical order)

			Adam Arsenault
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/adam_arsenault">tw</a>]</sup>,

			Adarsh Pallian
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/pallian">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/pallian">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Aki Kaltenbach
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/akikaltenbach">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/akikaltenbach">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Alanna Kostiw,

			Andrew Gray
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/uhAndrew">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/pub/andrew-gray/1/bba/87">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Alanna Rogers,

			Alex Grant
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/alexegrant">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/pub/alexander-grant/24/794/570">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Alexandrine Boissiere (i.e., "Alex"),

			Ambrosia Humphrey,

			Ana Levene,

			Andrew Soro (who goes by "Soro"),

			Ashley Jane Brookes,

			Andy Au,

			Beier Cai
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/beiercai">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/beiercai">ln</a>,
			<a href="http://beiercai.com/">web</a>]</sup>,

			Ben Watson,

			Bill Monkman
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/bmonkman">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/billmonkman">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Brian Lam,

			Bruce Xia,

			Bocar Dia,

			Carla Cristoffanini
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/carlacnini">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/pub/carla-cristoffanini/20/694/671">ln</a>,
			<a href="http://carlacnini.tumblr.com/">tmr</a>]</sup>,

			Cameron Uganec,

			Chris Maxwell,

			Chris Trottier,

			Christof Trafford,

			Connor Meakin,

			Craig Ryomoto,

			Daina Lightfoot,

			Dan Webster,

			Daniel Mathews (i.e., "Danny"),

			Dario Meli
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/quikness">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/dariomeli">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Darren Suomi,

			Dave Olson (i.e., "DaveO")
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/DaveOHoots">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://twitter.com/uncleweed">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://twitter.com/uncleweed">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/daveo">ln</a>,
			<a href="http://uncleweed.net/">blog</a>]</sup>,

			David Chan,

			David Go,

			David Tedman
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/d1337">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/davidtedman">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Destin Haynes,

			Diana Luong,

			Edward Steel,

			Eric Puchmayr,

			Felix Maldifassi,

			Garrett Eidsvig,

			Gary Morrison,

			Gavin McDonald,

			Grant Harris,

			Geordie Henderson,

			Gerard Recio,

			Greg Gunn,

			Greg Williams,

			Helen Park,

			Ian Bevis,

			Ian Robin,

			James Rumble,

			Jaxon Lam,

			Jenny Nguyen
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/neyugn">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/nguyenjenny">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Jeremy Pierre,

			Jeff Mills,

			Jeff Stautz,

			Jess Wakeman,

			Joanna Ambrosio,

			Joe Ying,

			Jordan Ng,
			Josh Lamb,
			Julien Emery,
			Katie Shindler,
			Kemp Edmonds,

			Ken Ho
			<sup>[<a href="https://twitter.com/shiunken">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/pub/ken-ho/35/730/46b">ln</a>,
			<a href="http://kenho.ca/">web</a>]</sup>,

			Kerri Bremner,
			Kingsley Chan,
			Kirsten Bailey,
			Kristine Naldoza,
			Louisa Thue,
			Lyndsay Tilston,
			Marcus Jung,
			Mark Eijsermans,
			Mark Holder,
			Matt Switzer,
			Melissa Joaquin,

			Michael Miner
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/m_p_miner">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/pub/michael-miner/16/835/184">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Michael Tan,
			Mohamed Zahid,

			Noel Pullen
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/noelpullen">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/noelpullen">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Nori Inoue,
			Paul Donnelly,
			Paul Semenets,
			Philipp Gebauer,
			Rahim Lalani,
			Rob Alderman,
			Rob Feduk,
			Ryan Delmaire,

			Ryan Holmes
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/invoker">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/rholmes">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Samantha Milbrath (i.e., "Sam")
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/sam_milbrath">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/sammilbrath">ln</a>,
			<a href="http://another9.tumblr.com/">tmr</a>,
			<a href="http://flickr.com/sammilbrath">fkr</a>
			<a href="http://www.onwhitewalls.com/">blog</a>]</sup>,

			Sandra Chung,
			Sandy Pell,
			Scott Walker,
			Sharad Mohan,
			Simon Stanlake,

			Stephanie Wiriahardja (i.e., "Steph")
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/stephawie">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/stephaniewiriahardja">ln</a>,
			<a href="http://www.thedandeliontheory.com/">web</a>]</sup>,

			Steve Johnson,
			Steve Mynett,
			Tasia Custode,

			Tatsuhiro Ujihisa (i.e., "Uji")
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/ujm">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/in/ujihisa">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Taylor Loren,
			Thiago Leite,

			Tracey Ferris
			<sup>[<a href="http://twitter.com/traceyferris">tw</a>,
			<a href="http://linkedin.com/pub/tracey-ferris/48/888/663">ln</a>]</sup>,

			Vanessa Fuller,
			Vicky Truong,
			Yasunori Mahata (i.e., "Yasu"),
			Zuo Zhou (i.e., "Geo"),
			#####
			and everyone else at HootSuite, in my #### capacity.
		</p>
		-->


		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
