<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-04-01T11:36:22-0700</published>

	<id>b8f63d12-8553-44af-8976-b58edf9b6ca1</id>

	<category term="HootSuite" />
	<category term="Marketing" />
	<category term="Owly" />

	<title>Community Building Talk</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			This isn't really the type of thing I usually blog about.
			This article serves as place for me to record some notes (on items I found interesting) from a talk <a rel="nofollow" href="http://uncleweed.net/">Dave Olson</a> (a.k.a. DaveO) gave to <abbr title="mainly HootSuite employees, and some others">a select audience</abbr>.
			(Perhaps this is standard marketing knowledge. Regardless, even if it is, it's new information to me.)
		</p>

		<h2>We Have The Technology</h2>
		<p>
			<a href="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/hootsuite_dance.jpg"><img
				src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/hootsuite_dance.jpg"
				align="left"
				style="margin-right:18px;margin-bottom:18px;width:18%;height:18%;border:1px solid black;"
			/></a>

			Although I have created technology used by people who engage in '<em>community building</em>', and I am cognizant of it and even knowledgable about it <em>to a degree</em> and could be considered to have some expertise on it from a <em>computational</em> point-of-view,
			from a "<i>boots on the ground</i>" point of view '<em>community building</em>' is <strong>not</strong> one of my areas of expertise.
		</p>
		<p>
			To use a simile.... I'm like the guy who engineers (who architects, designs, etc) the aircraft carrier, not the people manning it.
		</p>
		<p>
			But knowing the experience of the people using the technology you engineered can be helpful for the engineering process.
			It can also helpful for the product development process.
		</p>
		<p>
			I am also the type of person who likes to know how everything works, so even if I have not intention in engaging in the activity myself, I still find it interesting.
		</p>

		<h2>Story Time</h2>
		<p>
			<a href="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/daveohoots.jpg"><img
				src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/tn-daveohoots.jpg"
				align="right"
				style="margin-left:18px;margin-bottom:18px;width:18%;height:18%;border:1px solid black;"
			/></a>
			
			The talk, or '<em>story time</em>' with DaveO as it was framed, occurred (on Friday March 30th, 2010) over at the HootSuite offices.
			I don't think its main topic was meant to have been '<em>community building</em>' per se, but the telling the tale of the <a rel="nofollow" href="http://hootsx.tumblr.com/">HootSuite adventures at SXSW 2012</a> in Autism Texas.
			And also to talk about the HootBus, which most HootSuite people only found out about through tweets, photos, and media coverage.
		</p>
		<p>
			I think DaveO "fused" in some of the presentation he gave at SXSW 2012 into '<em>story time</em>'.
			(Which I found to be a boon.)
		</p>
		<p>
			As an aside, I suspect '<em>story time</em>' may have functioned as a <em>group-strengthening</em> exercise.
			It may have even been a concious goal.
			Perhaps there was a worry of "friction" within the group, due to only a select few getting to be part of the SXSW trip.
			(My suspicion; I don't really know.
			Keep in mind that there's "worse" ways to pursue <a href="http://changelog.ca/quote/2012/03/26/ingroups_outgroups_group_cohesion_and_the_ilongot">group-strengthening</a>.)
		</p>
		<p>
			Also, with respect to <em>group-strengthening</em>, (my observation was) the <em>HootSuite scarfs</em> they gave to everyone in the company (which they also gave out at SXSW 2012) probably helped.
			That and all the alcohol and (light?) partying following 'story time' probably also functioned towards <em>group-strengthening</em> (for most).
		</p>
		<p>
			But back to '<em>community building</em>'....
		</p>

		<h2>Community Building</h2>
		<p>
			<a href="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/hootsuite_community_board.jpg"><img
				src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/tn-hootsuite_community_board.jpg"
				align="left"
				style="margin-right:18px;margin-bottom:18px;width:20%;height:20%;border:1px solid black;"
			/></a>

			What is '<em>community building</em>'?
			I'll just quote DaveO:
			community building is "bringing these people together who are your <em>brand fans</em>, <em>evangelists</em> and <em>enthusiasts</em> and putting them together and letting them represent you in an informal way online".
		</p>
		<p>
			Isn't that just a kind of marketing?
			I suppose this is like a discussion of whether computer science is just math (or something else).
			(I think DaveO would say "no" though, that's it's not marketing.)
		</p>
		<p>
			Either way, the activity can have value, from a business point-of-view.
		</p>
		<p>
			(The <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/kk/6836521454/sizes/l/in/faves-uncleweed/">photo</a> to the top-left of the game board turned into presentation prop (by DaveO), was taken by <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/kk/">kk</a>.
			In the top-right corner of the game board you can see a physical real-world HootSuite badge, as opposed to a virtual one.
			The badges are mentioned later; if you want to see what they currently, at the time of writing, look like, look at the image.)
		</p>

		<h2>HootBus</h2>
		<p>
			<a rel="nofollow" href="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/hootbus.jpg"><img
				src="http://changelog.ca/log/2012/04/01/community_building_talk/hootbus.jpg"
				align="right"
				style="margin-left:18px;margin-bottom:18px;width:28%;height:28%;border:1px solid black;"
			/></a>

			In the time leading up to SXSW, there were actually (internal) rumors (at HootSuite) going on about the HootBus before it was built.
			But the details about it were very very vague.
			DaveO "<em>played his cards close to his chest</em>".
			(Or at least, if full details were being shared, they weren't being shared with me.
			I suppose I also wasn't interested enough, at the time, I seek out more details.)
		</p>
		<p>
			It actually ended up getting a lot of attention.
			(Which I think was the point.)
			On the blogs, on (online) social networks, and on MSM, such as <a rel="nofollow" href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303717304577278653746101734.html">The Wall Street Journal</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
			(The <a rel="nofollow" href="http://instagr.am/p/ICxAHrHWZx/">photo</a> of the HootBus, on the right, was taken by Justin Young a.k.a. <a rel="nofollow" href="http://twitter.com/justinyvr">@justinyvr</a>.
			The giant owl is '<em>Owly</em>', HootSuite's mascot.)
		</p>

		<h2>Signaling, Reputation and Creating Value</h2>
		<p>
			What can you give people if you're a start-up, and your budget (i.e., <em>money</em>) is "tight"?
			The answer is somewhat nuanced....
		</p>

			<h3>Creating Value</h3>
			<p>
				Although it was not framed this way in the talk -- in 'story time' -- one of the points was to 'create value' for things (beyond the cost to make them).
				Again, this can be important when you are in the world of start-ups, and budgets are "tight"!
			</p>
			<p>
				DaveO didn't give this example, but I think it's a good one that illustrates his point....
				Consider the medals that many military personal value (and may receive for valor, bravery, or a sacrafice).
				The amount of value many (if not most) soldiers give a medal goes way beyond the cost of the metal (and ribbon) it was made out of.
				Not everyone will receive such medals.
				The military does not sell their medals.
				I think some would probably suggest that "selling them would cheapen them".
				And a person selling a medal (they received) seems to tend to be treated as violating a taboo and even many non-military personal seem to find it offensive.
			</p>
			<p>
				How is this kind of value created?
				Part of it is by ensuring a scarcity:
				only creating a limited supply,
				and being highly restrictive of who you award them to.
			</p>
			<p>
				As part of the scarcity, it's important not to offer whatever prizes you have for sale.
				Once you do that, you set a monetary value to the item, which can deminish the value others put on it.
			</p>
			<p>
				For example, if you award (branded) t-shirts as a prize (and a 'thank you') for someone who did a month's worth of voluteer work, and then sell it for $15, the volunteer may interpret their month's worth of work as being worth $15 to you.
				(Which may discourage them for volunteering.)
				Keep the prizes scarce and be picky with who receives them.
				Make it so it is something <em>not everyone can have</em>.
			</p>
			<p>
				Perhaps all this is a play on <a href="http://changelog.ca/quote/2011/06/24/essentialist_theory_of_pleasure">people's <em>essentialist</em> nature</a>.
				Although there's likely <em>signaling</em> and <em>reputation</em> at play too.
			</p>
			<p>
				Just to be explicit, I might phrase this as "creating value", but it's important to remember that it's not you (the marketer or community builder) that is 'creating the value'.
				The <em>value</em> is <em>created</em> in the minds of other people.
				Value is a subjective thing.
				And not everyone is going to place the exact same value on each award of yours.
				(Some may not even find them valuable at all.)
				You (the marketer or community builder) are creating a situation that makes it more likely that people will value whatever it is you are awarding people;
				and are making sure you don't do thinking that diminish the value other people have for them.
			</p>

			<h3>Badges</h3>
			<p>
				T-shirts aren't the only thing you can award select members of 'community'.
				Another popular prize today are badges.
				(Although often virtual.)
			</p>
			<p>
				Badges (of the physical real-word variety) aren't a new thing to award people.
				There is a long history of badges being used to signify a (special) accomplishment.
				Today, this type of usage is seen in
				various military organizations,
				quazi-military youth organizations such as the scouts and other scout-like organization,
				and even in some schools.
			</p>
			<p>
				(As a side note, badges have also been used as
				fashion accessories,
				to mark an affiliation with an organization,
				as an indication of status or rank within an organization,
				etc.)
			</p>
			<p>
				Virtual badges are the latest iteration on the badge theme.
				These days they're all over the place, and are considered part of the "gamification" technique.
				You see them
				in video games,
				in online social networks such as Foursquare,
				in (the personal genomics company) 23andMe (as a way of encouraging customers to participate in their 23andWe research project by taking surveys).
				(Obviously not meant to be an exhaustive list.)
			</p>
			<p>
				DaveO has actually created physical badges as prizes and awards for people, in case the virtual/physical distinction mattered (to some).
			</p>

			<h3>Titles</h3>
			<p>
				Titles are things that can have a utilitarian value.
				In the business world, titles (like educational credentials and certifications) are (often) used by potential employers as proxies for quality.
				(It's a separate issue how good they are at this purpose. But either way, and perhaps more importantly...)
				They can have an effect on your employability for a particular job.
			</p>
			<p>
				However, and this a big however, (with the exception perhaps of some systemizers) most people have a more visceral reaction to titles.
				For most, (even if it isn't completely concious)  titles can serve purposes of signaling, status and authority.
			</p>
			<p>
				Having said all that, another thing that can be awarded to select members of your 'community' are: <em>titles</em>.
				(Just remember you are 'creating value' with <em>titles</em> too.)
			</p>

			<h3>Links</h3>
			<p>
				You can even give people links to their website, twitter account, or whatever.
			</p>

		<h2>More</h2>
		<p>
			All in all, I probably can't do this topic justice.
			And may have misunderstood some things and missed something.
			Either way, DaveO has
			<a rel="nofollow" href="http://uncleweed.net/">a blog</a>,
			<a rel="nofollow" href="http://twitter.com/uncleweed">a twitter account</a>,
			and <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/uncleweed/">a flickr account</a>.
			And of course, there's also his official HootSuite presence <a rel="nofollow" href="twitter.com/DaveOHoots">on twitter</a>.
		</p>

		<h2>Foreshadowing</h2>
		<p>
			It also wasn't lost on me that he "created value" with the <em>HootSuite scarfs</em> he gave everyone.
			And that he foreshadowed this in his talk.
		</p>


		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
