<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-04-06T11:07:12-0700</published>

	<id>41482a28-6252-46e8-a202-c086ca326989</id>

	<category term="Creativity" />

	<title>For Some, Writing Is Easy</title>

	<content type="xhtml">
	<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
		<p>
			For myself, it tends to take effort to put my thoughts into linear form (to write an article, a blog post, or an e-mail) if I want it to "sound good".
			But for some, writing is easy.
		</p>
		<p>
			For reasons I won't go into here, (one day) my brother was inside of a vehicle for an extended period of time.
			I think he was bored an wanted someone to talk to.
			Here's his text message to me (that was meant jokingly):
		</p>
		<blockquote>
			<p>
				Day 4:
				The outside world is becoming one of mystery to me...
				a distant memory.
				I do wonder what the outside world is like...
				being stuck in this cell.
				This cell might be 8.5' x 5'...
				but it only has a 4.5' ceiling height.
				It feels more like an obese man's casket than a cell.
				The walls feel like they're closing in...
				I don't know how much more I can take this.
				I send this message out to all that I can reach...
				in hopes that maybe someone will help my sanity.
			</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			Obviously, he's metaphorically comparing the vehicle he's in to a prison cell.
		</p>
		<p>
			My brother's jovial text messages  to me (which he writes without effort)  sound much more eloquent than my usual style of writing.
			To me (at least) it sounds like "novel quality".
		</p>
		<p>
			He followed that up with another one:
		</p>
		<blockquote>
			<p>
				Time sure moves slowly in here.
				Wish I knew what day it is...
				something most people take for granted.
				I watched the sun rise and now it looks as if its going to fall...
				yet time escapes me.
				It all looks the same in here.
				I try to keep time by scratching lines on the wall...
				but when I fall asleep I miss adding some of the lines.
				Which leaves me where I am now...
				in the vast unknown.
				Has time stopped or has it kept going...
			</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			His effortless joking text messages sound better than my effortful articles.
		</p>


		<address class="vcard">
			-- <a rel="author" class="fn n url" href="http://changelog.ca/"><span class="given-name">Charles</span> <span class="additional-name">Iliya</span> <span class="family-name">Krempeaux</span></a>
		</address>
	</div>
	</content>
</entry>
